Guide to the Stuart H. Patterson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stuart H. Patterson papers
1880-1963
WA MSS S-2612
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.96
(3 boxes)
The collection consists of letters, memoirs, photographs, annotated books, and other papers created and accumulated by Stuart Hayt Patterson, documenting his relationship with Ernest Thompson Seton and both men's experiences as ranch hands in New Mexico in the early 1890s. Highlights include drafts of Patterson's memoirs, featuring a chapter on Seton and the events that inspired Seton's book Wild Animals I Have Known (1898) and including rewrites by someone identified only as "Moore," letters from Seton and L. V. F. Randolph, annotated copies of Seton's books, and photographs of Patterson at various points in his life.
Patterson, Stuart Hayt
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Stuart Hayt Patterson (1871-circa 1954)
Stuart Hayt Patterson was born on 12 February 1871 in New York City, and grew up in the suburbs of New Jersey. He worked as a cowhand and lawman in Texas during the early 1890s. In 1893, Patterson befriended Ernest Thompson Seton while they were both working for the rancher L. V. F. Randolph, and the two remained lifelong friends. According to correspondence in the collection, the composite character of "the Dude" from Seton's autobiography, Trail of an Artist-Naturalist, was based in part on Patterson. Patterson returned to New York in 1894, and worked as an accountant and businessman, retiring as Vice President and Comptroller of the Guaranty Trust Company in 1940. He went on to write a memoir, which was never published, chronicling his time in the Southwest and his experiences with Seton.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of letters, memoirs, photographs, annotated books, and other papers created and accumulated by Stuart Hayt Patterson, documenting his relationship with Ernest Thompson Seton and both men's experiences as ranch hands in New Mexico in the early 1890s. Highlights include drafts of Patterson's memoirs, featuring a chapter on Seton and the events that inspired Seton's book Wild Animals I Have Known (1898) and including rewrites by someone identified only as "Moore," letters from Seton and L. V. F. Randolph, annotated copies of Seton's books, and photographs of Patterson at various points in his life.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged according to form or genre.
Ranchers -- New Mexico -- 19th century; Ranching -- New Mexico -- 19th century; New Mexico; Memoirs; Photographs; Patterson, Stuart Hayt; Randolph, L. V. F. (Lewis Van Syckel Fitz), 1838-1921; Seton, Ernest Thompson, 1860-1946; Seton, Julia M. (Julia Moss), 1889-1975
- Letters, 1893-1948; 4
  - L. V. F. Randolph to Stuart Hayt Patterson, 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ernest Thompson Seton to Stuart Hayt Patterson, 1894-1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ernest Thompson Seton to Helen M. Patterson (photostat), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Julia M. Seton to Stuart Hayt Patterson (photocopies), 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Memoirs, circa 1950; 9
  - "S. H. P.'s Rough Draft (Part 2)" (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
  - "Moore's final rewrite of 1st part" (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - "[Moore's final rewrite] of 2nd part" (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
- Photographs, circa 1880s-1900, undated; 4
  - Portraits of Stuart Hayt Patterson as a boy and young man (including 1 carte de visite and 2 cabinet cards), circa 1880s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Portraits of Stuart Hayt Patterson on horseback, 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Studio portrait of Stuart Hayt Patterson, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Snapshots of Stuart Hayt Patterson and Hayt Homestead in Patterson, New Jersey (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photograph of Tetons by Stuart Hayt Patterson
- Other Papers, 1922-1963; 7
  - Printed material relating to Ernest Thompson Seton, 1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings about Ernest Thompson Seton, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Printed material relating to Stuart Hayt Patterson, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Notes about Stuart Hayt Patterson (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Copy of Virginia H. Patterson's Will (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photocopies of material relating to collection (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Books by Ernest Thompson Seton, 1898-1943; 3
  - The Preacher of Cedar Mountain, inscribed to Patterson by Seton, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Trail of an Artist-Naturalist, including letters from Seton and a typescript account by Patterson of his acquaintance with Seton attached to the frontispiece and endpapers, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Wild Animals I Have Known, including a handwritten account by Patterson on front endpapers, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Oversize
  - Portraits of Stuart Hayt Patterson on horseback (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photograph of Tetons by Stuart Hayt Patterson (Box 3, Folder 29)